Guide to the Woman's College records, 1928-1974 UA.25.05.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Woman's College records
1928-1974
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Woman's College
UA.25.05.0001
60.4 Linear Feet 42,305 items
The Woman's College was established at Duke University in 1930, as a coordinate to Trinity College for men. As a coordinate college within Duke University, the Woman's College fostered a community that allowed for shared university faculty, curriculum, and educational facilities, while giving women an opportunity for leadership through their separate student government, social standards committees, and judicial board. It was merged with Trinity College in 1972. The collection includes university administrative records, correspondence, reports, memoranda, minutes, course schedules, statistics, handbooks, newsletters, calendars, financial information, photographs, audio recordings and other materials. Major topics include coordinate education at Duke University, especially administrative and curricular procedures; relationship between the Woman's College and its students (in loco parentis); social standards policies; women's student government; integration of the Woman's College; student health care; and student organizations.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Use of audiotapes and videotapes from this collection requires the creation of reference copies. Reference copies for some materials may have been made, and if a reference copy exists, it is noted in this finding aid. To arrange for the creation of reference copies of other items, please contact University Archives staff. Although these recordings are now stored in a stable environment, their condition and playback quality is unknown.
Provenance
The Woman's College records were received by the University Archives as a transfer at various times from the Woman's College and then after its dissolution from Trinity College.
Historical note
The Woman's College was established in 1930, as coordinate college to Trinity College for men, with the appointment of Alice M. Baldwin as Dean of the Woman's College. Prior to that women had a long history of attending Trinity College (the antecedent of Duke University). Three Giles sisters were awarded degrees in 1878 on the basis of private instruction by faculty members before Trinity College moved to Durham in 1892. In 1892 the Board of Trinity College officially admitted women to the college, and the first women to attend regular classes graduated in 1896. These women had been permitted to attend classes but they were not given residence on the campus.
In 1896, Washington Duke made a gift of $100,000 to Trinity College urging that women be admitted "on equal footing with men." A small dormitory, the Mary Duke Building was subsequently built in 1898; however it was torn down in 1912. It was replaced by Southgate dormitory for women in 1921. In 1903, Washington Duke removed the proviso attached to his 1897 gift in order to support academic liberty by removing all strings attached to his gift. By 1904 Trinity College had fifty-four women enrolled. The enrollment of women increased during the years of World War I as undergraduate men became scarce. The increase in women students gave rise to the instatement of a Dean of Women, Martha Buchanan, as well as the formation of the Woman's Student Government in 1918. In 1924, Alice M. Baldwin was named Dean of Women.
The establishment of the Woman's College in 1930 coincided with the movement of the men to the newly opened West Campus. The Woman's College was geographically distinct in that its administration building and dormitories were on East Campus (the old Trinity College Campus); however as a coordinate college within Duke University the Woman's College shared university faculty, curricula, and in most instances educational facilities with the other residential undergraduate arts and sciences college, Trinity.
The original enrollment, in 1930, was 506. Classes for freshmen and sophomore women were separate from those of the men and the women for the most part were taught on East Campus. In the 1950s and 1960s student interest in coeducation grew, and gradually coeducation became a reality in freshman and sophomore classes, as well, increasing intercampus travel. Enrollment increases occurred over time: during Dean Baldwin's tenure (1930-1947) enrollment increased to 1,000 students, and during Dean Brinkley's tenure (1947-1967) the enrollment increased from 1,000 to 1,262. This last increase in enrollment brought fundamental changes within the college. The Woman's College Student Government had operated in a town-hall fashion, but with the increase in enrollment the student body became too large to assemble together in the Woman's College Auditorium (renamed Alice M. Baldwin Auditorium in 1964). According to a report to President Knight entitled, The Woman's College in Duke University (1930-1969) submitted February 1969 this enrollment increase was partially attributed to changing student-government procedures and altering other college customs thereby making the student body less cohesive.
The completion of the new administration building (Allen) on West Campus in 1954 allowed for the record keeping and admissions to become centralized services. Thus the recorder and director of admissions for the Woman's College moved to the West Campus facilities. Further consolidation of campus life occurred when the Student Union, an all-university organization, was organized in 1954 on West Campus. This organization subsidized by the University, became the center of student activities for both men and women. However, three Woman's College organizations, the Freshmen Advisory Council, the Y.W.C.A., and the student government remained strong and active during the 1950s and early 1960s.
Dean Margaret Ball began her tenure of the Woman's College in 1963. Her charge as dean was to strengthen the autonomy of the College and to serve, along with the dean of Trinity College, as assistant dean of arts and sciences. Dean Ball also focused upon the physical facilities of East Campus establishing seminar rooms in several buildings, installing fire escapes, remodeling the old Dean's House into a Campus Center for students, remodeling various academic buildings for departmental uses, and installing a language lab, and computer card-punch room.
During the 1960s a perpetual request from the student body was the liberalizing of social regulations, especially those that were traditionally imposed upon women and not on men. This issue became a driving-force in the creation of a university unified student government (Associated Students of Duke University, ASDU) an organization that increasingly pressed for the elimination of all parietal concerns of the University.
Citing more efficient administrative procedures, more efficient representation of undergraduate education concerns and changes in social regulations and admissions' policy, in 1972 the Board of Trustees approved the merger of the Woman's College and Trinity College.
Dean of Woman's College
Alice M. Baldwin, 1930-1947
R. Florence Brinkley, 1947-1962
Ellen Huckabee, (acting), 1963
Margaret M. Ball, 1964-1969
Jane Philpott, (acting), 1969
Juanita Kreps, 1970-1972
Dean of Women
Martha Buchanan 1918-1919
Elizabeth Fronde Kennedy, 1919-1923
Alice M. Baldwin, 1924-1929
Mary Grace Wilson, 1952-1970
P. Philips, 1971-1972
Assistant Dean of Women
Lillian A. Lee (1961-1972)
Dean of Undergraduate Instruction
Ellen Huckabee, 1963-1967
Associate Dean of Instruction
Smith, 1937-1946
Ellen Huckabee, 1950-1951
Jenkins, 1950-1963
Jane Philpott, (acting) 1963
Jane Philpott, 1964-1967
Assistant Dean of Instruction
Ellen Huckabee, 1947-1949
Virginia S. Bryan, 1966-1967; 1969
Annie Leigh Broughton, (acting) 1967
Annie Leigh Broughton, 1968-1971
Josefina Tiryakin, (acting), 1968-1969
Elizabeth Nathans, 1972
Dean of Freshmen
Elizabeth Andrew Persons, 1943-1945
Annie Leigh Broughton, 1968-1969
Elizabeth Nathans
Dean of Residence
Mary Grace Wilson, 1938-1952
Director of Admissions for Woman's College
Elizabeth Anderson Persons, 1945-
Social Director of the Woman's College
Mary Grace Wilson, 1931-1936
Scope and Contents note
Materials in the collection include university administrative records, correspondence, reports, memoranda, minutes, course schedules, statistics, handbooks, newsletters, calendars, financial information, photographs, audio recordings, scrapbooks, and other materials from the tenures of Deans Baldwin, Brinkley, Ball, and Kreps. The university administrative records of other offices such as Dean of Women, Academic Dean, Assistant Dean of Women, and Dean of Freshmen are also present.
Collection Arrangement
The Woman's College records spans the years 1928-1974, although the bulk of the items in the collection span the years 1950-1972. The collection is arranged into the following series: Admissions, 1930-1971; Calendars, 1958-1965; Committees, 1945-1969; Freshmen, 1934-1973; Office of the Dean, 1928-1974; Statistical Reports, 1930-1960; Student Organization's Scrapbooks and Activities [Oversize], 1932-1969.
There is an index available for this collection onsite at the University Archives. Beside each series title in brackets is the reference number(s) for the index that are contained in that series. Reference numbers are also listed on each individual folder.
Separated Material
Several oversize technical drawings and blueprints were separated from the collection and placed in map drawer 37.
Related Material
Alice M. Baldwin papers, 1863-1961.
University Archives, Duke University.
Arts Council records, 1950-1970 (bulk 1950-1959).
University Archives, Duke University.
Charles E. Jordan papers, 1942-1966.
University Archives, Duke University.
College Organization for General Service records, 1940-1949.
University Archives, Duke University.
Freshman week [serial]: announcements and program / The Woman's College of Duke University.
University Archives, Duke University.
The Handbook for women students of Duke University [serial].
University Archives, Duke University.
Katharine M. Banham papers, 1910-1995.
University Archives, Duke University.
Office of Career Development and Continuing Education records, 1965-1976.
University Archives, Duke University.
Office of Continuing Education records, 1969-1992.
University Archives, Duke University.
Order of the White Duchy records, 1925-1968.
University Archives, Duke University.
Order of the White Duchy records, 1925-1968.
University Archives, Duke University.
Summary of the regulations of the Woman's College, Duke University [serial].
University Archives, Duke University.
Women's Department of Health and Physical Education records, 1923-1976.
University Archives, Duke University.
Women in higher education -- North Carolina -- Durham; Photographs; Women -- Education (Higher) -- North Carolina; Women -- Education (Higher) -- North Carolina -- Durham; Women -- Education -- North Carolina -- Durham -- History; Sound recordings; Duke University. Woman's College -- History; Baldwin, Alice M. (Alice Mary), 1879-1960; Duke University. Woman's College; Duke University. Woman's College -- Students
- Admissions, [O.A.], 1930-1971, 2 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  1.5 ln. ft. (about 1,000 items) Arrangement: alphabetical
  These files consist mainly of statistical data documenting the growth and development of the Woman's College alongside Trinity College. In the file "History and Trends," Mrs. W.S. Persons, Director of the Woman's College Admissions from 1945-1971, summarized much of the work of her office.
  - Admissions Policies, 1944-1971 (Box 1)
  - (Faculty) Advisory Committee on Admissions and Financial Aid, 1953-1967 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Questionnaire (Proposals), 1965 (Box 1)
  - Black Applicants, First Inquiries, 1957; 1960 [FERPA] (Box 1)
  - College Entrance Examination Board, 1945-1968 (Box 1)
  - Dormitory Space Reports, 1953-1968 (Box 1)
  - Duke Day, Durham High School, 1950-1953 (Box 1)
  - Form Letters, 1957-1969 (Box 1)
  - Forms (Applications), 1957-1970 (Box 1)
  - History and Trends, Woman's College, 1930-1954 (Box 1)
  - Manual of Procedures, July 1964 (Box 1)
  - National Association of Principals of Schools for Girls, 1948-1959 (Box 1)
  - National Association of Principals for Girls, 1960-1966 (Box 1)
  - National Registration Office for Independent Schools, 1957-1957 (Box 1)
  - Official Social Functions, Working Papers regarding arrangements, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Professional Education, Program Descriptions, General, Nursing, and Physical Therapy, 1947-1958 (Box 1)
  - Profiles, Statistics, and Projections, 1930-1968 (Box 1)
  - Schedules, 1958-1961 (Box 1)
  - Scholarships, A.B. Duke and National, 1952-1959 (Box 1)
  - Scholarships Foreign and Domestic, 1956-1969 (Box 2)
  - Scholarships, University Scholarship Committee, 1949-1961 (Box 2)
  - Seminar, 1957-1958 (Box 2)
  - Special Procedure for Processing of Decisions on Applications for Women, 1963-1965 (Box 2)
  - Staff Communications (East), 1953-1966 (Box 2)
  - Staff Communications (West), 1961-1968 (Box 2)
  - Statistics and Reports, 1932-1967 [FERPA] (Box 2)
  - Statistics and Reports, "Recruitment and its Expansion," 1950 Travel, 1950-1968 (Box 2)
  - Yearly Reports, 1930-1971 (Box 2)
- Calendars,[CD] 1958-1965, 7 boxes
  3.5 ln. ft. (about 2,000 items) Arrangement: chronologically
  The calendars record all events scheduled in the Office of the Dean of Women. The files include details such as the room reservation for meetings, the time of the event, the sponsoring individual or organization, and any special requirements. The calendars also include brochures, announcements, etc. of certain publicized events.
  - Calendar, Dean's Office, June 1958 - Nov. 1959 (Box 3)
  - Calendar, Dean's Office, Dec. 1959 - Jan. 1961 (Box 4)
  - Calendar, Dean's Office, Jan. 1961 - Jan. 1962 (Box 5)
  - Calendar, Dean's Office, Jan. 1962 - Nov. 1962 (Box 6)
  - Calendar, Dean's Office, Nov. 1962 - Nov. 1963 (Box 7)
  - Calendar, Dean's Office, Nov. 1963 - Jan. 1965 (Box 8)
  - Calendar, Dean's Office, Feb. 1965 - Aug. 1965 (Box 9)
- Committees, 1945-1969, 1 boxes
  - Development Advisory Committee, 1964-1969[WCDAC]. (see also the same title in the Office of the Dean series, below)
    0.5 ln. ft. (about 150 items) Arrangement: alphabetically
    These files were taken from the Mary Irene Elizabeth Kistler Clyde papers, Chairman of the Development Advisory Committee. They contain general information concerning membership in the Development Advisory Committee and include correspondence some of which deals with continuing education for women.
    - Woman's College [Development] Advisory Committee, 1964-1965 (Box 10)
    - Woman's College [Development] Advisory Committee, Correspondence, 1965-1969 (Box 10)
    - Woman's College [Development] Advisory Committee, Minutes, 1965-1966 (Box 10)
  - Scholarship Committee, 1945-1969, [SCH]. (see also Scholarships, Alice M. Baldwin Scholarship Committee in the Office of the Dean series, below and Scholarship Committee in the Dean of Freshmen subseries, below)
    These files are the combination of several Scholarship Committee files into one collection, and include items such as "The Alice M. Baldwin Scholarships. Report of Progress," financial reports, samples of Christmas note paper printed for the Baldwin Scholarship Fund, and the annual report of the Duke University Woman's College Scholarships.
    - Woman's College Scholarship Committee, 1945-1960; 1969 (Box 10)
- Freshmen, 1934-1973, 13 boxes
  - Dean of Freshmen, 1938; 1952-1973, [DF65-72].
    2.0 ln. ft. (about 4500 items) Arrangement: alphabetically
    - Academic Council, 1969-1973 (Box 11)
    - Academic Guide for Freshmen, 1968-1971 (Box 11)
    - Academic Performance Studies, 1966-1971 [FERPA] (Box 11)
    - ACE Questionnaire, 1971-1972 (Box 11)
    - Admissions Advisory Committee and Information, 1966-1972 (Box 11)
    - Admissions and Financial Aid, University Committee on, 1967-1969 (Box 11)
    - Advanced Placement Tests, 1963-1970 (Box 11)
    - Affirmative Action Plan, 1972 (Box 11)
    - Alumnae Spring Weekend, 1967-1968 (Box 11)
    - Angier B. Duke Scholars 1966-1972 (Box 12)
    - Annual Report, 1965-1970 (Box 12)
    - Annual Report, supporting documents, 1966-1970 (Box 12)
    - Art, East Duke, 1966-1971 (see also Art, East Duke in the Office of the Dean series below) (Box 12)
    - Assistant Dean of Instruction, Responsibilities of (Annie Leigh Broughton), 1969-1971 [FERPA] (Box 12)
    - Assemblies, 1968-1970 (see also Freshmen Class Council, below) (Box 12)
    - Averages, grade point, 1964; 1967-1969 (Box 12)
    - Black Students, 1969, black studies program, "Beauty of Black" week, Allen Building protest (Box 13)
    - Board of Visitors, 1971 (see also Curriculum Revision, below) (Box 13)
    - Bus Schedules, 1971 (Box 13)
    - Calendars, University, 1967; 1969-1972 (Box 13)
    - Class Honors, 1966-1972 (Box 13)
    - Class Structure Committee Report, 1966-1967 (Box 13)
    - Community Council of the Woman's College (CCWC), 1971, n.d. (see also Community Council of the Woman's College in the Office of the Dean series, below) (Box 13)
    - Continuing Education for Women, Center for, 1967-1971 (Box 13)
    - Counseling Services, 1964-1970 (Box 13)
    - Curriculum Report, 1960-1961; 1969 (Box 13)
    - Curriculum Revision, 1966-1971 see also Board of Visitors, above) (Box 14)
    - Dechaine Study, 1971 (Box 14)
    - Degree Requirements, 1969-1971 (Box 14)
    - Directors of Undergraduate Study (DUS) and Supervisors of Freshmen Instruction, 1969-1972 (Box 14)
    - Drugs, newspaper reports, form letters, university and state regulations, 1966-1971 (see also Drugs in the Office of the Dean series, below) (Box 14)
    - Duke University United Fund Drive, 1970 (Box 14)
    - Engineering, College of, 1964-1971 (Box 14)
    - Experimental Group, Classes of 1970-1973 [FERPA] (Box 14)
    - Faculty Advisors Program, 1969-1971 (Box 15)
    - Faculty Meetings, 1969-1972 (Box 15)
    - Federations, student lists, 1971-1972 (Box 15)
    - Federation, Baldwin, 1971-1972 (Box 15)
    - Federation, Few, 1971 (Box 15)
    - Federation Kilgo, 1971-1973 (Box 15)
    - Finances, 1963-1970 (Box 15)
    - Freshmen Advisory Council (FAC), selection and training, 1966-1973 (Box 15)
    - Freshmen Class Council, 1964-1971 (Box 15)
    - Freshmen Summer Reading Lists, 1965-1970 (Box 15)
    - Freshmen Orientation, non-Duke, 1966-1972 (Box 15)
    - Freshmen Week Evaluations, 1967-1969 (see also Freshmen Week subseries below) (Box 16)
    - Freshmen Week President's Reception, 1964-1971 (Box 16)
    - Health, 1965-1970 (Box 16)
    - Honors Assembly, 1970-1972 (Box 16)
    - Honors, Committee on, 1972 (Box 16)
    - Housing Problem, 1967-1970 (Box 16)
    - Information, Notices, and Appointments 1965-1971 (Box 16)
    - Internships in Community Service, 1968; 1971 (Box 16)
    - January Freshmen, 1971-1972 (Box 16)
    - Joint Deans Group (Undergraduate Schools and Colleges), meetings, 1967-1969 (see also Joint Deans Meetings in the Office of the Dean series, below) (Box 16)
    - Judiciary Committee, reports and recommendations, 1969-1972 (Box 16)
    - Krueger, Robert, Vice Provost and Dean of Trinity College Arts and Sciences, memos from, 1972 (Box 16)
    - Language Placement, 1962-1969 (Box 16)
    - Learning Disorders, 1968-1970 (Box 16)
    - Leaves of Absence, 1967-1969 (Box 16)
    - Libraries, 1969 (Box 17)
    - Living-Learning Corridors, 1966-1970 (see also Living-Learning Experiments in the Office of the Dean series, below) (Box 17)
    - Living-Learning Corridors: Social Sciences, 1966 (Box 17)
    - Majors, 1967-1971 (Box 17)
    - Mathematics, Department of, 1967-1972 (Box 17)
    - Memos, Woman's College Staff, 1971-1972 (Box 17)
    - Music, Department of, 1970 (Box 17)
    - Nathans, Elizabeth, Assistant Dean of Instruction, miscellaneous correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 17)
    - North Carolina Association of Academic Deans, 1969-1971 (Box 17)
    - North Carolina College Personnel Association, 1968 (Box 17)
    - Physical Education, 1969-1971 (Box 17)
    - Physical Therapy, Graduate Program, 1970 (Box 17)
    - Policies and Procedures, 1963-1972 (Box 17)
    - Pre-Law Advising, 1968-1972 (Box 17)
    - Pre-Med Advising, 1964-1970 (Box 17)
    - Pre-Registration, 1967-1972 (Box 17)
    - Pre-Registration Correspondence, 1971 (Box 18)
    - Proficiency Examinations, 1970-1972 (Box 18)
    - Program II, 1969-1970 (Box 18)
    - Protests, 1968-1971 (Box 18)
    - "Reading Out" of Courses, 1963-1968 (Box 18)
    - Registration, 1969-1970 (Box 18)
    - Residential Life Committee, Report, 1969-1973 (Box 18)
    - Scholarship Committee, 1956-1965 (for specific scholarship information see individual scholarship titles) (Box 18)
    - Scholarship Committee, 1965-1968 (Box 18)
    - Scholarship Committee, 1968-1970; 1972 (see also Woman's College Scholarship Committee in the Committees series, above, and Scholarships, Alice M. Baldwin Scholarship Committee in the Office of the Dean series) (Box 19)
    - Scholarship Financial Statements, 1971-1972 (Box 19)
    - Secondary School Counselors, Conference for, 1964-1970 (see also the same title in the Office of the Dean series, below) (Box 19)
    - Sororities, 1958; 1968-1970 (see also Sororities in the Office of the Dean series, below) (Box 19)
    - Staff Meetings, 1970-1971 (Box 19)
    - Stow, Ann Barbour Scholarship 1971-1972 (Box 19)
    - Student Employment, 1952; 1969-1970 (Box 19)
    - Study Abroad, 1966-1969 (Box 19)
    - Summer Session, 1967; 1972 (Box 19)
    - Summer Transitional Program, 1969-1971 [FERPA] (Box 19)
    - Symposium, "Woman's Role in Contemporary Society," 1967 (see also the same title as well as Symposiums, Duke in the Office of the Dean series, below) (Box 19)
    - Teacher's College Book Prize, 1969-1970 (Box 19)
    - Teacher Education, 1968-1969 (Box 19)
    - Transfer Credit, 1965-1971 (Box 19)
    - Tutors, 1967-1971 (Box 19)
    - Withdrawals, 1939; 1966-1970 (Box 19)
    - YWCA, 1967-1972 (see also the same title in the Office of the Dean series, below) (Box 19)
  - Freshmen Advisory Council (FAC), 1953-1974.
    0.5 ln. ft. (about 500 items) Arrangement: alphabetically
    - Chairmen's Notebook (Caryn McTighe), 1965 (Box 20)
    - Freshmen Advisory Council (FAC), 1966-1974 (Box 20)
  - Freshmen Week, 1934-1973, [F.W.].
    1.5 ln. ft. (about 1,500 items)Arrangement: chronologically
    - 1964-1966 (Box 21)
    - 1966, Planning (Box 21)
    - 1967-1969 (Box 22)
    - 1967, Planning (Box 22)
    - 1969-1973 (Box 23)
    - Freshmen Week Programs, 1934-1940; 1943-1945; 1947-1969; 1971 (Box 23)
- Office of the Dean.1928-1974
  - Alphabetical Subject Files, 1928-1974 [Dc60s; MGW38-70; OD25-70; OD25-72; OD30-71; OD43-63; OD45-72; OD45-72; OD62-72; OD63-71; ODc60s; ODMF63-73; ODMGW33-69]., 24 boxes
    36.5 ln. ft. (about 24,000 items) Arrangement: alphabetically
    University administrative records, correspondence, reports, memoranda, minutes, course schedules, statistics, handbooks, newsletters, calendars, financial information, photographs, audio recordings, and other materials from the tenures of Deans Baldwin, Brinkley, Ball, and Kreps. The university administrative records of other offices such as Dean of Women, Academic Dean, Assistant Dean of Women, and Dean of Freshmen are also present.